That must have been a really long day.
It was
today. I was obviously here all day.
Actually, it looked like I missed some
meetings today. I assure you, I work
really hard. I really do. All right. This
is actually, I think, going to be the most
exciting part of the day. This is the
final discussion. I am going to ask and we
didn't plan on some chairs. Could we get a
couple chairs just for some of this? We're
actually going to discuss how are we going
to move forward. We have enough brain
power in this room. We have enough
policymaking authority. We have the
ability to create legislation. We had
Senator Kullimore here earlier, our Senate
majority leader. I've already heard
there's going to be discussions happening
with some other state Senate majority
leaders. We have counterparts parts and
states. We have companies we work with. So
now the discussion for this last hour
before we leave is how do we move forward?
You never want to have a summit like this
without some outcome and some
deliverables. We have a lot of momentum
built and in order to keep this going, you
don't stop. That's what usually slows
government down is then you go back and
you review. So the question is how do we
keep the momentum going? I think three
will be good. So we're going to ask
Representative Cutler to come up and then
is Alan Fuller? in here? Alan, if you'll
come up. So this is we're going to have
we'll just have one mic for us to share,
but then the rest of the mics we'll have
some interns around and we want to discuss
what are we doing next? What are our next
action items from our side? But then how
do we engage with states to go ahead and
get this consortium going? And then I see
the clock here says 14 minutes, but I
think we're just at the end, right? So we
haven't four timers, right? Okay. So let's
actually check.
I think it'd be beneficial if we explain
some of what our next steps are actually
going to be. Alan, do you want to take the
first? Let me just get started by saying
that Senate Bill 260 gave the Department
of Government Operations of which Chris
and I and Marvin Dodge was here are a part
are all part of and it tasks us with
coming back to the legislature with a
specific proposal and the input we receive
here and the input we receive through a
request for information that we put out
many of you responded to that RFI. Thank
you for that. We over the next couple of
months are going to be putting together a
proposal to go back to the legislature for
our SEDI program going forward. And you
know, we live in the real world. We have
to, if we're going to create a system
that's going to have provide identity for
millions of people in the state, it has to
be something that works really well as
performant and secure as private. And so
all of the principles that we've talked
about today need to eventually come
together in a real life system that
actually works. Maybe we can turn over to
you and represent Cutler. Sure. One of the
thoughts that I have is in order to, we
can, I mentioned this before, we can pass
the policy, but we need our industry
partners and we need a large enough
coalition that we have a critical mass. So
what you can do to help is encourage our
industry partners that you, by telling
them, look, I'm interested in in this or
let's work together to get something done.
Communicating that you're interested in
being part of a critical mass to move this
forward, even if we don't necessarily
agree on all the finer points, I think is
really important. I thought the gentleman
from the blockchain co-inventor that was
real wisdom that working together, even if
it's not perfect, we can make a tremendous
impact. So, but we can't do this without
our industry partners pushing very, very
hard and getting products that we can put
in an alpha phase or a beta phase and
start testing and finding the flaws and
finding the successes.
Two practical things that I think we can
expand. Here in Utah for the last couple
months, we've actually held a private
sector stakeholder group every Friday we
meet, whether we're exhausted or not, to
engage with the private sector. I do think
we should expand that to invite all
private sector in other states. If you are
ready to participate and you want to
engage, you want to help be part of
building the solution, we can expand that
and get that set up so you can come and
coordinate. And this doesn't have to just
be a Utah stakeholder group. This is part
of the SEDI consortium. How do we make
sure everybody's engaged and
participating? We want a diverse set of
ideas, you know, so long as you love
constitutional rights. And but I think,
you know, we all have a role to play here.
And for the private market, there's always
going to be money to play. You can bring
real value-added services. We don't want
government to be doing beyond the bare
minimum of providing a foundation to
protect individuals. So this is amazing
for you. This is going to be really
disruptive in a good way to move that
money from incumbent players to others
that can help create a more competitive
marketplace. So that's one thing we'll do
right away. We'll open that up. I'll start
on the communication for that and get
invites out set next week. I think we had
the National Chamber of Commerce
Foundation here today as well. So I'm
assuming you might be able to help us with
that as well. How do we get this out to
all the businesses that are part of that?
The other thing is now that we're through
the summit, we need to go back and start
defining some of those baseline
requirements. What are the requirements
we're going to compare technology to and
everybody should play a part in that.
Obviously the RFI is closed. We have a was
it a thousand or thirteen hundred pages to
read. We have twelve hundred pages to read
and I know we don't have all the info we
need. So we're going to need everyone to
participate to say what additional
requirements are we missing? And then
comes the hard work of the technology
needs to prove itself. How do you meet the
requirements? And then also I think to
what you said earlier the hierarchy of
values. That's going to be the hardest
part. I know a lot of people in this room
are concerned that we are going to
compromise on the wrong things in the name
of interoperability and efficiency. So as
we define the requirements, we're going to
have to create this hierarchy of values,
which I have seen nowhere. I think that
slide was the first time I've seen that
presented in that way to have technology
value at the highest level of that
constitutional rights. So that's going to
be a hard part in the requirements
building list. but that's the type of
stuff that's going to build trust with the
public when they see what we are
prioritizing. And I think it's going to be
great. I think it's actually going to be
great for government. Trust is at an all
-time low. So this is a really good way to
be very transparent to an extreme and let
them know that we really want to protect
them. One of the things I think that we
should talk a lot about is something that
Ryan brought up earlier in his
presentation about the kind of practical
side of rolling something like this out.
and gaining adoption. We need to find a
launch customer that not maybe customer is
not the right word, but a launch tenant
that can help us that will pick this up
and run with it maybe in Utah like a Zions
Bank or something like that that will help
launch the whole process and also create
the system in such a way that it
incentivizes use rather than
disincentivizing use. in order to get
adoption. One of the big problems that we
have with our current MDL program in Utah
is that by charging the verifiers for the
verification software, it's a disincentive
for them to verify. And that makes it so
you got an MDL that people can walk around
with on their phone, but there's not very
many places it can be used. So then you
have not very much adoption. And we want
to set this up systematically so that it
will have adoption and incentives to use
from the beginning.
– Kristen Allen, if people have ideas for
use cases, where do they go? And I think
I'm thinking back to our experience with
verifiable digital credentials. We didn't
start with the most critical key. We
started with something easy that no one
was it wasn't controversial. Though I
think maybe there's some lessons learned
here that How do we start this and get
some use cases where we can learn from
before scaling it? And what are your
thoughts on that process? Well, I was
thinking they should call the legislator.
All the
RFI responses are protected, but I think I
can semi-quote what was in them. One of
the best ones that I read was it was
actually from an entity that's not looking
to compete. They were just giving advice
of how they could best serve their
customers with this. And they said, and
this is actually a saying, I was in
health, uh, human services for seven years
before this role. Um, they said in that
RFI response, help us meet the clients
where they are, meet people where the use
cases are. Um, and so they said, you know,
TSA probably was not the best example.
That's not something that, you know,
everybody is going to need, but there's
lots of people who have their kids going
to school every year. They need to, uh, to
enroll and need to have a birth
certificate or immunization records. There
are use cases where we don't have to try
to replicate what's already being done
with MDL and is working and they're
getting traction on that side. What are
other use cases that we can tackle to
tackle other more complex issues that are
a different subset of individuals, but
it's meeting people where they are and
they're going to use it. And government's
great. I love the saying, government can
actually do almost whatever it wants
because it's the only entity that can have
a legal monopoly. So the only thing
stopping us from getting the credentials
out to where they're needed in a secure
way and getting these use cases is I think
that's the legislature. Speaking of the
legislature. You need money. Yeah, if we
need money, we know who to talk to. You
know, this is not just about us talking.
We really want to this is audience
participation. I really wanted to maybe
start by asking the audience some
questions, especially can I start with the
legislators in the room? What do you feel
like you've seen today or what questions
do you have coming out of the
conversations today? Would anybody like to
please?
And introduce yourself too.
Okay. Knowledge is power and you know
getting more of us in the room or you know
legislative trainings, et cetera, because
it's hard to vote for something if you're
insecure or ignorant of an issue. You're
less apt to vote for something or even
make any kind of progress if you are
unsure of what you're voting for, which is
a good thing. You don't want your
legislators voting on things that they
don't know about. So I think increase, I
see a handful of us here today. Maybe it's
because my colleagues just know all the
things, but I've certainly learned a lot
today. Appreciate especially those
presenters who really broke it down into
simplistic terms for me. And, you know,
I'm a lot more comfortable. I was never
against, not completely against it, but I
definitely feel more comfortable after the
things I've learned today. So I would just
say, especially with our lawmakers, we
need them. We need us in a room so that
everyone can understand and then make the
decision based on that. And I think that,
you know, the more people learn, the more
comfortable they'll be with the direction
that we're heading. Thank you.
Anyone else? Questions out there? Yeah,
let's open up to everyone. Other thoughts
and…
Thank
you.
Were you the one that works with the
anatomy labs? Who is that? Anonymy Labs?
No, he's over there. Steve McCown. So, I
use MySudo. That's, yep. Excellent. I was
curious. So, you're asking how we can
implement this technology into that. I
mean, is this something that's being
implemented into MySudo? We do a wide
variety of credentials. We implement and
support a wide variety of credentials. And
so, SEDI is definitely on our roadmap.
out. What? Okay. Well, that's awesome. And
I just think that this is excellent
technology. My limited understanding so
far, but I think from some of the policies
that we've seen get passed, the app store
identification, forgetting SB, whichever
one that was, and just a variety of bills
that Utah has passed has been, you know,
for the children. It's kind of like the
the messaging push behind it, but it's
devastating to internet privacy and
anonymity. like we've talked about some of
these here, in my opinion. And I think
that SEDI is one of the technologies that
can bridge that gap and that can really
help us. And my understanding right now,
it seems like this is some vital
technology. So I just, I'm championing,
you know, everyone here working on this.
It's great. So. Thank you. Question over
here. So maybe not so much a question.
It's just, you know, you talked about what
use cases and things that you can do to
make it move forward. So Eric Jorgensen,
I'm the motor vehicle director out of
Arizona. Jonah, fantastic conversation and
discussion this week. Thank you very much
for today for putting it on. I think a
couple of things that I would just want to
say that I think would be key was one is,
you know, we already have a great head
start on this with MDL, right? So somebody
early on said, hey, let's not worry about
the technology aspect of it. This is
really about the underpinning policies.
And I will tell you, I've been involved
with MDL for the past. 10 years almost.
Over 10 years now. And I haven't heard a
single thing today that like butts heads
with that technology. And the good news is
when we talk about adoption, 60% of the US
population is covered by a state that
issues a MDL today. So we already have it.
And in Arizona, by the way, we have over 1
.2 million MDLs issued. We have a
population of 5.6 million driver's
licenses out there. Biggest use case is
not TSA. It's the motor vehicle division.
It's state services. We use it now. We
used it in a pre part seven ISO compliant
way to do it, but we had it out there. We
consume our own MDL and that became one of
the biggest use cases. Massive driver for
adoption for us. So something to think
about and something that is in your
control as you look at it is why not use
it yourselves? That's a place where you
can control both sides of the equation and
make sure not only is the provisioning
done in a privacy-preserving and secure
way, but the consumption too and set kind
of that example for everybody else on how
to consume it too. So just a thought.
That's terrific. And also let's
acknowledge Chris Keras. Chris, if you
could raise your hand. He's the director
of our our driver's license division here
in the state of Utah has done a terrific
job leading our MDL program. We're
grateful for him. I think Jimmy Higgs is
here as well somewhere. I don't see him at
the moment who will be the next driver's
license division lead after Chris retires.
We are I believe that my expectation and
hope and this was mentioned to me today
too from someone else that likely the
states who are already doing MDL will be
the first adopters of moving to more broad
study because they kind of get it and have
already invested in creating a credential
like that. Let's see. I think I saw a hand
up here. I think it was was it Sarah or
Okay,
we'll go here and then back. Oh, yeah,
Amelia, please. Yeah. I know that I've
obviously been working on this with you
guys for years. Introduce yourself,
Amelia. My name is Amelia Powers Gardner.
I'm a county commissioner in Utah County.
And I've been working on decentralized ID
and self-sovereign identity since 2019 pre
-COVID. And, you know, as I look for as a
county commissioner in the fastest growing
county in the state, we're 43.6% of the
state's growth. As I'm starting to look at
capital projects and building brick and
mortar to the tune of tens of millions of
dollars because of for a growing
population, the sooner we can get these
services instituted in a way that we can
start utilizing them to deliver services
to our citizens in a secure, private way,
that prevents me from having to spend
millions of dollars. And so my question
comes in, like, I know we've got the
groundwork, but I mean, you know me, I'm
like, I want to run first. I want to run
first and then I want to walk and then I
want to crawl on. We do need backwards
compatibility, but when are we going to
have the ability for an organization like
mine that has already done some of this
work? when are you going to give us the
ability to start adopting this on a broad
scale? When do I start getting the schema
and the requirements so that I can start
implementing this for my citizens so that
I can deliver services to my citizens
without having to spend tens of millions
of dollars building brick and mortar
buildings? Was that chastising us, Amelia?
I'm joking. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So there's a
lot actually going on in Utah for those
that are from other states and just, you
know, we work with Amelia all the time. So
we've had this discussion. For every
state, you actually have a unique
opportunity right now. Every state
nationwide is pretty much non-compliant
with their records management and data
governance laws. And Amelia is shaking her
head, but this is the opportunity. So when
I say that, what I mean is you all have
antiquated laws from the 70s and 80s that
require certain things like disposal of
data according to retention schedules.
Most systems have not been created to
dispose of data. Most states haven't
established the purpose and use of data.
Most states haven't been giving privacy
notices. And that sounds really bad, but
the great thing about it means there needs
to be a modernization anyway over the next
decade. And so you're in the unique spot
of because you know there's non-compliance
and I'll actually I'll share out after if
one of my team can take a note, we had
interns over the summer actually research
all 50 states' laws to determine where
they are legislation-wise. So you can see
where is your state with privacy, with
records management, with data governance.
You'll know you're non-compliant, but now
that you know what's coming with digital
identity, you know you need data
governance. And now what Amelia mentioned
is the schemas, this concept of what are
the rules? What's the schema? What's the
formats of the data that needs to be
collected? When Amelia is asking what's
the schema, it's hey, when somebody
applies for a building permit. What is the
exact data the county should be
collecting? What needs to be on the forum
so they can automatically ingest it,
automate that process with AI or machine
learning, and then move toward the
efficiency that government can get. So
what I'm saying is now is actually the
perfect time to learn where you are. And
it takes about a decade to transform. Utah
is about three years in on this journey.
And that's why we've been modernizing our
laws. We've been getting comprehensive
privacy law. Amelia, but the schemas will
come sooner. We actually have on our team
we're doing modernization of then the data
governance structures, the rules around
the data, how long can you keep it? What's
the legal basis? What's the purpose and
purposes and uses? We're starting to
define what are the immutable records,
which records are immutable public
permanent records, which makes sense to go
on a blockchain. These are the things you
need in a schema to then implement
technology correctly. If you jump right to
the technology without having these
things, you end up having to backtrack. So
I don't know if that's the answer, but
it's coming soon. And the schemas I think
will be very soon. We have some almost
ready. Maybe Sarah? I just want to echo
thanks again for having this event. It has
been really, really powerful learning a
ton and getting to make sort of leaps and
bounds forward. So thank you. I think
there's an opportunity to create a more
sort of like formal digital space where
those things that you were just talking
about, Chris, if you could post them,
playbooks, I think this opportunity of how
can we learn from you also share what we
are doing in Colorado and other states so
that we can learn together. I was
reflecting on the statement about MDL and
opportunities around MDL. We recently
discovered that the standard MDL contract
with the big tech wallet companies, Apple,
Google, Samsung, in our case, have a
clause in them that says they are sole and
exclusive provisioner and revoker of MDL.
And like, that's something I want to share
with you all about like one particular
thing, because it does conflict with the
SEDI idea. And so how do we join forces
together and say like, hey, Apple, Google,
let's not have that as the standard
clause. Yeah. All of us are sort of
against that idea. So I think that there
is an ask maybe and how can we contribute?
It's not just an ask of you. Can we host
it? Can we do something so that we can do
that knowledge sharing and really
accelerate our co-growth? We will be
emailing out after the summit. One,
obviously we had the white paper of what
is SEDI. We have some resources that we've
created of model legislation, model
resolutions, model executive orders. For
us to do a formal consortium, there should
be something you want your elected
officials, governor or legislature to
authorize. We've had this discussion with
our governor and let him know we wanted to
do a consortium, which is why we've
invited you all today. If one more state
for, I mean, we've had a couple reach out
and say, actually, we're very interested.
If you can get the formal approval, we'll
start seDI.gov. And it's not seDI.Utah
.gov, seDI.gov. You need at least two
states with formal approval. And that's
where we start building that multi-state
formal consortium and we can start then
advocating for ourselves and for our
citizens and put these resources there and
we can build it together.
Yeah, that works. Okay. So first of all,
thank you. This is actually turned out
very well as an event and I think there's
been a lot of really great interest. I
always talk about this as an idea when we
talk about off-Broadway use cases as
representative Kohler mentioned, but I
think the idea of vital records is
something that is not so much any having
anything really implemented yet. And I
always like to say death records because
everyone needs one one day. Death and
taxes are the two things that they say are
inevitable. And there's a guardianship
mechanism and a burial permit mechanism
and a plot of land. Kind of have
everything at once. I do have him the
treasurer of a cemetery, so I would love
some funds. We're actually going to have
George McKeown make a comment about how
are we engaging vital records. The amazing
thing actually about government is once we
start saying we want to do something, it
opens doors with all these organizations.
I wasn't anticipating getting on stage. So
one of the things we've done is we've
reached out to Napsus and I just gave a
discussion to their security and privacy
group last week. We are actually talking
about the schema that they have for a
national standard for a certified birth
certificate and their digital schema. So
we have committed that if they want us to
come out to their December event, we will
bring a SEDI compatible version of that.
So they're close on their standard. We
just need to wrap it in the appropriate
cryptography to make sure that meets the
SEDI threshold. And I think we'll be
there. The real goal will be is in June of
next year when they have their annual
event that will really move that forward
with them and kind of codify all that.
One of the this session as we go in to
make recommendations for the SEDI program
and we also we need to recommend what
would the next legislation look like part
of that does need to be prioritization of
credentials and that's been a very common
ask. How do we get these other value-added
credentials not just mobile driver's
license or a driving credential but it was
birth certificate, your immunization
records, your death certificate and And so
I would anticipate that would be part of
the discussion we have this session is not
only do we need to get it out there, but
then we need to work with the group. So we
had I think we had part of the group group
here from health and human services today
where vital records is, but I think that
is a low hanging fruit use case to get out
there. We'd actually love to know what are
you going to use that data for if people
have it? What's the private sector able to
provide value for if you have those
records though? And Scott, I think you had
a question, right? I have three things.
One, excellent day, really outstanding.
Two, incrementalism is important, but
there's a cart and a horse kind of aspect
to this. And so, how do you get to trust?
And I think that's one thing that we
really need to ask ourselves in terms of
who is trusted to each of us. And if
that's our teacher, our professor, our
doctor, our lawyer, our banker, I mean
where that comes in, I think really it
might help you define use cases and how to
go after those early and first. And third,
if you want an example of one state that
I, if you went to Hawaii anytime during
the pandemic, Hawaii did a really
excellent job of making sure that they
could reopen their economy, which is
tourism, by making sure that they had the
smart health card for people to come in
and show proof. You had to prove you were
vaccinated in order to visit at that time.
And they did a really a great job of it.
People were motivated, of course, to fill
this out and an ID for it. But it's just
one example that you might want to loop in
Hawaii on.
All right. So listening to all the
constituents here, the challenge I think
that we have here is a scope problem.
There's lots of things that can be done,
but the way to get something done is
iterative. And it needs to start with the
core of what you're looking for. So you've
done two things. You've said, we're going
to have a state endorsed identity. Okay.
And you have a law. So you have two things
to build upon. I think you start there.
What is the state going to do whether you
have paper to present to the state to
endorse, but it has to be focused on the
first and foremost thing, which is how do
we issue a state-endorsed digital identity
and start there? And then use cases will
come once you have that established. If
you don't have that established, what's
the SEDI project? So that needs to be the
absolute core, and it needs to start with
a risk assessment because there's a
million risks we talk about today. but
there are only certain risks that can be
mitigated by a project like this. And that
will drive the scope of how you can
mitigate the risk to the degree that the
state can accept. And you take the law and
all the requirements that you have in the
law and put it in the governance framework
and the set of requirements. And at least
you are have you have momentum. You need
to start with momentum and leadership and
others will come and use cases will come.
But it has to be right down the road for
what you've done. Don't lose focus on
that. You have law to drive a state
-endorsed digital identity. Make that
happen. You have the means to do it and
you have the expertise in the room here to
start for sure.
So Matthew Helston here from Brigham Young
University and I think transcripts and
educational data is a very complex use
case and been working on this since 2016
with SSI space and we've made a long way
so it's really amazing but I wanted to
emphasize something that I think about
with decentralized identity I think is
important is that just because we have a
credential and a set credential doesn't
mean we have a ubiquitous identifier. So
we don't want to have a unique identifier
that correlates us wherever we go. We have
the possibility of using that identifier
where we want to, but we can create an
ephemeral identifier with our credential
and make a connection with another entity
to present our information. That's really
important that when we think of our use
cases, we're not thinking of I can be
correlated wherever in that a great user
experience and that may be true, but I may
not want that as an individual and the
technology needs to support the privacy
policy of me being able to choose to
create an identifier to present my
interface and my information through. So I
want to emphasize that. Another thing I
wanted to emphasize is credentials need to
be intentional. They don't have to be
where everything is stored in one
credential, right? I can have a very micro
credential for a specific intended purpose
and the technology stack allows me to take
multiple credentials and draw selective
disclosure information from each of them
and aggregate it into a presentation for
the verifier. So that means as an issuer
of a credential I don't have to solve all
my use cases where I think my credential
is going to be used. I just have to focus
on my data and give that to the
individual. individual and let the
verifier define their own data contract
that really empowers them from a data
model perspective of verifier defines
their contract and we can fulfill it from
a number of credentials. We can give an
example of that with our the first
credential and this is what representative
Cutler is referring to is our off-highway
vehicle training certificate which we put
out a verifiable digital credential for
this training certificate to drive your
four-wheeler on the roads. Yeah, thank
you. And we have, but it doesn't say who
you are. So you still, it doesn't provide
your identity. You have to have both an
identity and this credential to say, you
know, who you are and that you've taken
the course. Let's see, where are we with
our microphones? Maybe here. Yeah, go
ahead. Yeah. Phil Long from the US Chamber
of Commerce Foundation and T3 Innovation
Network. I just want to bring us back to
the actually the first presentation that
was given this morning by Ryan First.
first who are Ryan. Yeah. That reminded us
that we really need to look at the
examples of failures of the things that
we're looking at as potential priorities
to try to learn from them because we tend
to dismiss that was done by them. It was
done at a different time perhaps a year
ago. It may not be relevant, but there are
things and lessons in there that will be
extremely valuable if you look for them.
So that's one thing. And the second to
reinforce several of the comments here,
which is to pick the two or three to start
with that are win-wins for all of the
stakeholders involved because everybody's
going to have resistance to it at some
point in this early stage. So where you
can come up with one where there's
beneficial time savings for a government
office to get something done, that time
savings benefits the individual who's
making a request and the benefit of the
credential actually has direct value to
that person for what they're trying to do.
Those combinations are absolutely critical
and I applaud you for doing all of this.
Thank you. Do we still have Jeremy Grant
here? I'm going to steal a line that he
said, we can't build identity or what did
he call it? It says we can't build
identity or we're a bunch of identity
weenies building identity for other
identity weenies. And so we can't be
identity nerds trying to build this really
small use case of like, Yeah, it'd be
great to use a verifiable credential to… I
don't know, Timothy, what's a really weird
use case? You can probably think of one
off your head. What? Okay. You got a use
case? Oh, yeah. What about the beekeepers
license? Okay. Beekeepers license. That's
a pretty small use case. And does
government go and actually check beekeeper
licenses? So, but we have to build
identity for people that it's going to
have value and we have to meet them where
they are. How are they going to get value?
How is government going to get some value?
And I think that's also where I said we
have the ability because we are a monopoly
to solve the catch-22 of well let's create
that instance where both can get value and
we're already spending money on it. So
it's let's move those resources to
actually realize the savings that can come
from that. All right. So who has ideas of
how we can work together with other
government entities?
Hello, hello. My name is Mariano, Mariano
Green. I'm from Mexico City. I'm very glad
to be here with you guys. Even though that
I'm born Mexican-American, I'm more
Mexican than American. I live most of my
life there in Mexico. So I have learned a
lot with you guys how we can implement. We
have been working with clear companies,
try to like develop the Mexican an
environment there. But we came to the
conclusion that it has to be a grassroots
movement. It has to be with the
communities. The community has to endorse
their own, not only the identity, like
yes, identity has to be more broad, but
it's something that this movement has to
be more locally. I have been talking with
some of these persons here and a lot of
those persons came to the same conclusion,
you know? And that's the way that I think
personally the human being has to like has
to move towards to that because if not
that will happen with centralization and
control power. We all know that. So this
idea of stay indoors, I will say it more
like community indoors. That's my grain of
salt. I like that community indoors. One
of the I had the opportunity I think it
was as representative Chevrier still here.
She invited me to speak at one of her
events for Stand for Health Freedom a
couple weeks ago. And we had a really
interesting discussion of you mentioned
community of how to decentralize the
proofing process out into the community. A
lot of cities and towns and school
districts or even our post offices are in
the community. Do you need to go
essentially to a DMV to do proofing or can
we have lots of entities doing it? Move it
out to the community so there's more trust
because these are their neighbors that
work out there. If you can standardize the
identity verification and proofing
process, there's some real low-hanging
fruit and we can eliminate some of those
inefficiencies or barriers for people that
can't get it currently. And if you could
just go to your local city recorder or
your local treasurer or your local postal
office, why don't you have all the
options? And that's, I think, a great way
to get that grassroots going of those
communities that want it. We know Utah
County and some small cities have been
saying we want it. If we could build it,
bring it out to them. Pat Brooks with the
state of Missouri judiciary.
I'm not sure how many people here are
familiar with the standard called NEEM.
Anyone familiar with NEEM? NEEM is the
national information exchange model and
that started as what was the predecessor
of that was called GJXDM and that was a
global justice data exchange change model.
And what you're talking about doing here
is following the same path that that
program followed. You have a grassroots
follow along with the gentleman just
before that people had a need to do
something and the standards were
established and not so much in legislation
but in adoption from a technology
perspective to say this is how we can get
the work done. Going back to the comments
of publishing schemas, publishing
standards that people can adopt. And the
organization that started that was a multi
-state organization and it was in the
justice domain. And what happened to it
was it saw a need to exchange information
in multiple domains. And identity is one
of those domains. And so I would encourage
you to make sure that if we're
establishing a standard for multiple
states to follow that we look at if there
is RA something at the national level that
could be more readily adopted than maybe
building something from total to scratch.
You have governance that you have to
issue. You have to have vitality issues.
You have technology standards. But I think
this is a wonderful idea and I think that
it can be well served to see how others
have done something similar and going
forward.
Michael Proper, I have seen this dilemma
that we've been building and sitting upon
for years, well over a decade actually,
and the solutions right in front of us.
But will we really see it? And what I mean
by that is we know that we've all got to
come together and adopt a system and we
know that there's a political side of it
and there's a technology side of it. But
what if they really existed? Would you
really adopt them? Would you really use
them? Even if it had the beekeeper
scenario built into it and 86 other
certificates, permits, licenses that
already exist and already use these
standards. standards. Would you really use
it? Would the state of Utah really use it?
Would the state of Arizona really use it?
Would Mexico really use it? Mexico doesn't
know. It's a community thing. It's the
person that would actually be the ultimate
decision maker if they're going to use it.
That's why MDL has such… I think Arizona
has a ton of adoption. 17% adoption. If we
could do that with a decentralized system
where the individual actually will throw.
If we could do the same 20% of MDL energy
into a decentralized system and people
knew about it, the awareness and adoption
would go through the roof because it's
around the individual first. If we want to
be true and honest around what's going on,
Cindy who has a son that's dead is one
very small proof. It's not just a person's
life and their breath that's gone. It's
their time on earth that sucked from them,
from these corporations. Whether they're
slumming around pornography or they're
slumming around video games that are
taking the youth. Or we're allowing AI to
be able to replicate and take not just
from the next generation, the
grandparents, our parents, our children.
This is our responsibility. In Hawaii,
it's our kuleana. It's our time. And I
look at what Chris and Phil and Sam and
Tim, these people have dedicated decades
of their life. I too, 19 years, $28
million of my own hard-earned money into
this technology for the state, for the
countries, other countries, for no price.
Would you really adopt it? Would you
really look at it? Because if you do it
here and you can do 10% of what we're
talking about, other states will get on
board with it. If you give it back to the
individuals and truly let them own their
own identity, their own data, their own
payments, their own assets, and pass it to
the next generation, instead of the state
sucking out hundreds of millions of
dollars of unclaimed assets because people
don't even know where they are. The
technology is here today. It's not just in
some proprietary phone that's really open.
It's not about a phone. Even though
Cindy's parents, Cindy's son, that's how
they that's how he took his life. That's
how they stole him. As a parent of six
kids, I want to be able to say, I did
everything that I could. So that my son
that went to this university And when I
sat on the board of this university, when
her son killed himself, was responsible
enough to say, you know what? Enough is
enough. We got to stop the games. We got
to come together with the policy. We got
to come together with the technology. And
we have to actually act. Charlie Kirk was
killed 500 feet from here, 150 feet from
here. The action behind his choice network
was all what it's about acting. It's about
doing. The technology's here. People have
seen it. People can live it. They can
adopt it. You can download it. Utah life.
Go to your app store, download it, log in.
It's simple. This isn't hypothetical.
These are real systems that really
function better than Bitcoin, better than
Ethereum, better than the banking system,
better than the current identity
management systems. And I'm sorry, I want
to slow down and I want to just let the
process take its process. And Chris, I
emphatically support everything that
you're doing. But we don't have time. We
don't have another 10 years for another
decade worth of kids to not only stick
bullets in their heads, but to stick bits
in their heads that takes them away from
the life that they've been given. It
steals their time. It steals their souls.
It steals their hearts. I'm sorry that
this means so much to me. But I can see
the solution.
Thank you, Michael. And our timeline is
that 10 years is data governance. Our time
on lists is as fast as we can. Senator
Collin Moore said this on KUTV last week
and he said, we have to get it right. You
know, we don't want to cause more harm,
but the time is as fast as we can get out
there. So parents and individuals have the
tool. So that's our timeline and that's
our commitment is we're trying to get it
out as fast as we can. Obviously, we have
to follow the law, but we understand the
importance and that it's needed now. This
is not something that we want regular
bureaucracy to just sit on. And I think
that's why we're all here. This is not
normal bureaucracy. This is not a normal
meeting. This is something different is
happening and this is going to get done
right.
I'm not going to try to follow that, but
my question is for those in the private
sector partners who are helping us, what
can we do to help move this faster?
Understanding that we have to do it right,
but how can we move faster? Tim, should we
go here?
I've been working in the space for over a
decade now. It's like trying to push a
really heavy rock uphill really hard. A
lot of failure. A lot of things we tried
in different ways that didn't work and
then very optimistic about SEDI and what's
happening in the state level? I think the
answer, I've always been a small
government guy. And the reality is that
now that government is getting into the
digital identity space, it's several
decades behind private industry and
private industry has turned the digital
identity space into this just incredible
surveillance mechanism. But now
government's getting into the digital
identity space. And government at the end
you said has the monopoly on whatever it
decides to do. Government will dictate how
much privacy or freedom or autonomy we
have or don't have in the digital realm is
my prediction after all I've seen. So to
answer your question about how to finally
solve this, I think Utah has to be
successful in getting other states and
create momentum. I know that Utah has
deprioritized interoperability, which is
really interesting when you look at Utah's
hierarchy of values for a lot of identity
initiatives specifically, but technology
in general, the highest priority is
interoperability. And so what gets
sacrificed is security and privacy.
Specifically with the MDL standard, there
was a country that said we need to have
phone home and they didn't call it that.
We need to have server retrieval and it
was baked into the standard because a
country demanded it. Different culture.
It's not our culture. Someone else's
culture demanded it. It got baked in. A
bunch of us squawked about this a couple
few months ago and they have now separated
it thankfully. But the point is that was
made earlier.
We as Utah need to do what's best for
Utahns if even if it means that we're not
interoperable with the rest of the world.
We have to deprioritize interoperability
and do what's best for the privacy and
security of our citizens. And so what I
think is the answer to your question is to
get Utah to be more than just Utah that's
doing this, to get some representatives
from other states who are here to actually
move forward and join. It reminds me of
the end of the movie, A Bug's Life, where
the grasshoppers were were bullying the
ants through the whole movie. And finally,
at the very end, the ants realize they're
more powerful if they lock arms. I, I,
this digital identity community thing is
so big and I see grasshoppers everywhere
who are the bullies in digital identity
and I think the only way we do it is
Utah's an ant and we need to lock lock
arms with other ants and scare the
grasshoppers out of this space.
My name is Jeremy Furster from Cardano
Foundation in Veridian and I'm going to
say that I'm in the technologist camp or
stakeholder group. And normally when
speaking to policymakers, there is a view
from technologists that you're way off the
mark with what you're presenting as
policy. However, that is not the case at
all when coming to SEDI. And I think the
engagement that you receive and the
interest that you're receiving, the reason
why it's so high is because fundamentally
the policy makes sense for the
constituents. We've been able to
demonstrate with our demo that today SEDI
is not just policy. It can be codified. It
can be implemented. And I would ask, do
you see a path where you can eat your own
dog food? Because when you look to
implement SEDI, you need that first user.
A very easy low-hanging fruit could be
having a SEDI wallet to have a
passwordless login to a government
website. And if you do something like
this, it's very low risk to actually get
things started and have something put into
production that is end-to-end.
Well, I'm going to make a quick comment
because I actually got some text. I get
texts every weekend, just you guys know
from citizens that are like, I hate this.
What are you doing? And they actually sent
a text and you may have been about to go
here where they're going to say, Hey, They
were like, what is this Utah ID I now need
to use to log into a system? It's a just a
single sign-on portal, which any it's any
single sign-on system is going to have
tracking. It's a centralized. Yeah, it's a
username password type system. So there's
low hanging fruit. And I think there's
discussions already happening. So we know
constituents have identified the system.
They actually have said they want SEDI on.
We have the man here in charge of it. So
we have a couple of initiatives that we're
working on. And we have first of all, we
have our we have in a beta form our next
version citizen portal which we branded
MyUtah and you'll probably see Governor
Cox making an announcement about this
early next year. But the goal and we don't
have this quite here yet. I'm looking at
but we'll be getting there where we hope
to be able to have people authenticate
with a SEDI credential for that. And we
don't quite have the SEDI credential yet
to do that, but we want it. And so that'll
be one of our first and best use cases to
get that going. And we also want to look
at state systems. So we have our 22,000
state employees and we have identity and
access management that we log them into
our state system and we like to have a
SEDI credential so that they can log in as
employees and we would like to move away
from passwords even with our multifactor.
We don't love them. We'd like to move to a
more secure SEDI type credential for login
and use in identity and access management
systems across the state. hopefully
that'll be one place we can start to get
rolling.
I'm Mark Allen. I'm with Citizen Portal,
my brother today, Ancestry.com and we're
trying to work towards government
transparency and accountability. And
Chris, you're spot on when you say that
most of the state of Utah is not
compliant. I think our stats show about 15
% of public meetings are being recorded
gavel to gavel. I think some of the low
-hanging fruit that I'd suggest for
authentication and certification would be
within your own home of state government.
I have been branded a vexatious litigant
as of last night, but the judge of Charlie
Kirk case because I asked for a court
record. Let that sink in. I asked for a
WebEx video hearing.
I can't get anybody in the state of Utah
to give me a certified record. When I'm
doing grammar, they say, oh, it's a
duplicate request. I want state certified,
authenticated, genuine record that I can
take to the bank and say, I'm innocent.
But when I ask for that, I get branded a
vexatious litigant. So my admission
admonition as a state and county delegate
is also with what we're doing is clean up
your own house first, not at your level,
but at the clerk level where they won't
give me a certified record where the
keyboard is the weapon of today. And I'm
the first victim probably in the state of
Utah of lawfare. And, but if I had
everything that you've been talking about
today, SETA, ability to authenticate,
ability to track back into the record to
see who was the ghost that hit the
keyboard word to backdate a record by two
years. I wouldn't be as smart as I am now,
but I've learned a lot in the last 10
years and I'd say Utah, let's get it right
first. Let's start in the judiciary where
the problems are. And then my personal
identifying information, I can control and
protect it, but mine's been scattered to
databases around the world. And I don't
know how to undamage what that's been
done. We also have a problem with all
three branches of government in Utah.
They're not watchdogging each other.
There's not enough healthy friction. I'd
like to see a little more healthy friction
between stuff. So, and this is not
specific SETI related. It really is civil
rights, my personal protections. And I
don't need to go deeper down that because
I really appreciate what you're trying to
do. If we would have had implemented what
you did, what you're talking about 10
years ago, my life would be totally
different. But I've seen how China
weaponizes and surveils. I've been
surveilled in Utah, Provo, Utah. So court
certified records, definitions are really
important. What's a certified record? What
does a certified record look like to you
if I go down to the court and try and get
a digital copy or something that someone
will go, oh, this is, we made a mistake.
How do we undo the mistake. So that's a
personal use case scenario, but I think
our courts they don't on a standard basis
do a transcript. You can't get a certified
record unless I pay for it. $2,500 for me
to get a certified record. So I would
start within the court judiciary and start
certifying records and start doing court
transcripts if it were me. That's low
hanging fruit that would benefit most of
Utah. Thank you, Mark. We are All right.
We're going to have one more question.
We're at time, but Jeremy Baker is a Utah
privacy commissioner. If you don't know,
governance structure in Utah, we have a
whole commission dedicated to privacy. So
take that back to your state if you don't
have one. Go ahead, Jeremy. So I'm
actually going to take this from a
different perspective, and this is from my
private sector experience with being
someone that integrates security and
identity into software applications. And
it's related to how do we get the private
sector to adopt this. A lot of private
sector companies like even Roblox or
others, they end up using identity
providers like AWS Cognito, Okta, Azure,
B2C. All of those they've added in
different integrations for identities. So
you have like your social media logins
that are allowed in there as well as like
the current adoption of passkeys, which
has been really slow to roll out across
the entire private sector even though
they're significantly better idea than
passwords and usernames. But to get SEDI
adopted across all of them, I think the
framework like what we've talked about
today having an open framework where those
major identity providers could bring that
integration in as an authentication
service under the umbrella to have it as
an option to add directly into
applications that are currently working
with their products. I think that that
would be a significant push for adoption.
– Thank you, Jeremy. Okay, we're going to
close up first by raising hands who wants
to help get SEDI going forward. Okay. And
if it's not up, okay, everyone got it up.
And that was the worst thing to do because
I am shameless. One of my tricks in
government is I have no problem asking for
your time. So you will all be getting
calls in your states to move this forward
and we'll be shameless together to take
this national. We are so thankful that
everyone came today. I know this is a long
day and this was a lot of information, but
you now are ready to actually have the in
-depth discussions. So we will go back.
We'll do some of the grunt work to get
organized. We'll set up and we'll make our
materials available. We'll reach out to
the states to get at least one more
formally involved so we can get seDI.gov
.going going at seDI.Utah.gov doesn't have
the same, you know, ring to it. We want
seDI.gov. But we'll get rolling on that
and And we're going to meet back here
again in less than six months for the next
SEDI summit. And from what we're already
hearing, it's probably going to be twice
as big. And by that point, with the pace
we're going, not only will we have more
legislation, but hopefully we have a lot
more to share so other states can take it,
steal from our tax dollars and take it to
your state so you don't have to pay for
it. And let's get SEDI rolling. So thank
you everyone. Max Max Max Max Max Max Max
Max Max Max Max Max Max Max Max Max Max
Max Max Max Max Max Max Thank you.